I used to write
off storytelling like it
was some sort of
hippie nonsense because I
just couldn't understand how
something that we tell
kids at bedtime could
possibly appeal to adults
and grow a channel
or a business. In
fact, I was so
anti -story when I
was struggling to get
traction on YouTube, I
intentionally avoided it because
I wanted to prove
you didn't actually need
it. Remember how I
said I had an
ego? But eventually, when
I realized that no
one was going to
take me seriously unless
I could prove that
my way of growing
YouTube channels worked better
than the big creators
in my niche who
were teaching something completely
different, I was forced
into telling one to
show people how I
blew up a channel
in a few weeks
and that video got
millions of views. After
that, I was hooked.
Every time I planned
a video, I was
looking for a story,
something real, something emotional,
something human, something that
could pull the viewer
in and prove results.
And it worked again
and again and again.
In fact, this one
story filled up an
entire cohort. Now, at
that point, I stopped
fighting it and I
realized Tony Robbins, Simon
Sinek, Steve Jobs, pretty
much all of the
biggest personal brands and
every TED talker ever
in the world were
right because they all
say that storytelling is
the most powerful skill
you can develop if
you want to grow
a business. So in
this video, I'm going
to show you how
to use storytelling inside
of your emotion brick.
You're going to learn
the mistakes to avoid,
you're going to learn
how to plan a
story fast, and you're
going to learn the
three types of stories
you can tell that
lead to sales, views,
leads, and success. So
let's get started. Fans
who keep coming back.
All right. So to
start, let's look at
why stories hit different
and make information feel
new, easy, and inspiring.
So stories do three
things that pure information
pretty much can never
do. Firstly, they create
emotion and they make
your viewers gravitate towards
you when you tell
a highly relatable one
about a problem that
they have too. Secondly,
they activate 22 more
memory pathways in a
viewer's brain than facts
alone
can do. So it's
a very simple way
to build trust. So
if you're a viewer,
you can build trust
fast because you can
build trust fast because
you can build trust
fast because you can
build trust fast because
a story is often
you talking about how
you or a client
did something to solve
a problem your viewers
have too. So it
just provides proof that
you are legit and
differentiates you. But also
when your viewers feel
something like curiosity or
empathy or surprise, the
brain's hippocampus lights up,
which is responsible for
long -term memory. So
viewers just remember them
more than anything else.
And that is why
you can remember them
more than anything else.
So if you can't
remember the entire plot
to your favourite film,
but you can't remember
every step of an
Ikea desk build manual.
And it's why I've
opened most of the
videos you're watching in
this entire program with
a story. Oh my
gosh, Ed's using what
he teaches on me.
Yep. If you've only
just realised, I pretty
much always do. But
on top of that,
stories are just insanely
powerful for sales. It's
almost a little bit
freaky how powerful. So
let's take this video,
for example. I told
a story about how
I was very ill.
I had parasites. I
was trying to grow
a business. I was
trying to grow a
business. And the business
was going so fast.
I only had a
couple of hours a
day and I felt
awful and I was
miserable and I just
wanted to retire. And
I didn't realise then,
but it was my
biggest Bruce Banner to
Hulk transformation period of
all time. I then,
as a result of
that pain, figured out
some solutions to solve
it. And in the
video, I said how
now I was the
happiest I'd ever been
and how easy my
life was. So I
post the video. The
next day, I wake
up to a WhatsApp
message from a very
large, well -known channel.
And it just says,
Ed, can we have
a chat? That story
you told about how
you were feeling is
exactly what I'm going
through. Do you think
you could help me
get out of the
mess? In fact, throughout
the history of telling
stories in my videos,
the amount of clients
who have referenced just
one small one back
to me as one
of the reasons they
wanted to work with
me is absolutely mind
-blowing. So the way
I teach you to
write stories is not
just going to grow
a channel. It's going
to get your business
blowing up too. And
we're going to use
storytelling in all of
the advanced modules, which
is why I was
like,
discourse first, because it's
the foundations we're going
to build everything else
on. Okay, so now
you know why they
matter so much. Let's
look at how to
use them in a
video. And the way
to think of it
that's going to stop
you thinking that your
viewers just want raw
information with no stupid
stories is you're not
telling a story instead
of making a point.
You tell a story
to set up your
point so that your
viewers then want to
listen to the action
steps that follow. Then
after the story, you
transition into the logic
brick and give them
the steps to get
the results your story
was all about. This
makes the point stick,
and resonate because they're
emotionally primed to care
about what's coming up
next. So for example,
let's say you're teaching
how to price a
digital product. We don't
have to tell this
giant end -to -end
story. So you could
start like this. So
when I launched my
first course, I priced
it at $49 because
I was scared to
charge more. I worked
for three months, made
$900 and realized, ah,
I've built myself a
minimum wage job. And
if I wanted to
earn even more, I'd
end up with a
minimum wage prison. So
that's why I'm teaching
you how to price
a digital product. So
that's the story. Then
you would transition to
the logic and say
something like, so here's
how to price your
offer the smart way
using my three -part
value ladder. So that's
it in its very
basics. So now let's
break down how to
actually plan a great
story for your emotion
brick, which you've already
learned the foundations of
when we did the
demo video. And it's
this, we start with
the problem, you share
the action you took,
and then you show
the outcome. And that's
kind of all you
need. So let's go
deeper on how to
do that. So what
I want you to
do is I want
you to think of
every good story as
a circle. And you
can see here, it
starts with the problem
and then it moves
through to the action.
And then it ends
with the outcome that
reveals if the problem
the entire story was
about was solved or
not. When this happens,
the viewer is going
to get closure and
they're going to go,
ah, the problem was
solved or it wasn't.
That makes sense now.
Now, if the outcome
has nothing to do
with the problem you
started with, the viewer
is going to be
left thinking, wait, what
the heck was the
point? And then they're
going to comment nasty
things. And you're going
to blame story, not
yourself for telling a
bad one. Let's go
deeper on each section
of the story circle,
starting with the problem
or as it's better
known, the beginning. So
all you want to
do here is this.
I remember staring at
the screen, watching my
50th YouTube video, the
one I spent 10
hours editing, pulling only
12 views. And I
realized nothing they teach
you works. You see
what I did there?
I dropped a viewer
into the exact moment
where a problem felt
the utmost worse. And
that is what your
story's beginning should do.
If you nail this,
you will get sales
coming in from people
going, oh my gosh,
that's the exact problem
I have right now
too. Because when the
viewer sees themselves in
your story, they lean
in, they watch for
longer and they warm
up faster. And they're
also going to care
more about the solution
that follows. So when
planning, you just ask
yourself, what's the relatable
problem I want to
show the viewer how
to solve. And then
don't start at the
beginning of the journey,
start at the pain
point
and keep this to
like one to two
sentence max. It's very
important you are specific
with the language you
use here and make
sure you're using language
that hits on real
emotion or frustration or
confusion or embarrassment or
fear. Because if you
say I wasn't feeling
that great, that doesn't
create a vivid mental
picture in a viewer's
mind. But if I
said to you, I've
not slept for 48
hours, you potentially have
a vision of me
lying in bed, wide
awake, struggling. So specific
language is critical for
telling a great story.
And that's what I'm
going to do here.
So I'm going to
start with the beginning
of the story. And
then I'm going to
start with the action
of what you did
to start fixing it.
Otherwise known as the
middle. I know, right?
You didn't expect it
to be called the
middle after that bit
was called the beginning.
Did you? Mind blowing
stuff this, you're going
to freak out when
you realize what this
bit's called. Anyway. All
right. So let me
just show you the
big trap you need
to avoid when you
are doing your middle
piece. So a while
back, I spent months
thinking,
when I was writing
the books or thinking
I was briefing, have
I done okay? Because
I was not doing
okay and I was
not talking about myself.
receive enough Basically, for
our next one, nothing
but good things. So
you just have to
start with a nice
one. time to just
say, hey, I'm kind
of out of here.
tablespoon.
But before you start
writing more points, here,
try me all three.
So a piece will
be on whatever you
like. Stay with one,
New York. I'm just
going to start with
aradasal스 and then tell
us about initial comments
you want to use
in my book. If
you blue box out
of that 동의 grading,
how long will it
take if you don't
learn that really quickly,
you'd be lost with
a raise on those
comments or multiple但, surprise
result for me. Just
make the entire story
about that. And that's
what I did. And
it worked amazingly well.
So that's the thing.
You can cover more
than like one thing
in a story, but
really for a short
story and to practice
this, just pick one
choice you made, one
decision that helped you
or someone else shift
momentum towards the outcome.
And at the very
max, cover three things,
but never go further
than that because the
story's job isn't to
give them all the
information, it's to inspire
them. So an example
of that could be,
so I swapped the
main photo in the
Airbnb listing for something
that actually showed off
the space. That's it.
That could be the
action. It could just
be one to two
lines if you like.
Now, if you can't
decide what action should
I show, just ask
this, what's the most
surprising action that I
took that started solving
the problem? And then
just focus on that.
Again, you need to
avoid vague language like,
I got better or,
so I decided to
change my mindset. Or
my personal favorite, so
I decided to try
something different and it
worked. That doesn't give
the viewer anything to
connect to or anything
they could imagine doing.
And it sounds like
a lie. Oh, I
was just sitting there
with this problem. So
I thought, why don't
I try something different?
Oh, and it works.
Yay. And then once
you've nailed the action,
we move on to
the third and final
part of your story,
the outcome, which is
otherwise known as, you
guessed it, the Mangotini
Frappalopoulos. I'm just kidding.
It's called the end.
This is the moment
where you just, reveal
what happened. And here's
the thing. The outcome
doesn't need to be
positive. It can be
a win. It can
be a loss. It
can be a surprising
lesson learned. All that
really matters is there
has been a very
big transformation between here
at the start and
here at the end.
So it could be
something like the revised
Airbnb listing got booked
three times that week
and it's never been
empty again. So this
is the moment where
your viewers will think
to themselves, ah, this
actually works. There's proof.
I want that result
too. Or they go,
oh, okay. It didn't
work, but wow, that
lesson they learned from
it. Knowing that has
saved me years trying
to do this. And
that's what makes them
then open to the
logic brick that follows.
Now, one more powerhouse
for ending a video,
which might help you
pick the story you
tell is the reason
why you remember the
Sixth Sense and Inception
and the Penguin series,
because right at the
end, something happened that
totally surprised you with
a twist. So if
your story makes viewers
think the end is
going to be one
thing, and then it's
totally different from what
they expected in a
good way, not a
confusing way, tell that
story. But if the
end of your story
and the beginning are
very similar and there's
hardly any transformation, don't
tell it. It's a
boring story. Now, the
thing about this is
coming up with stories
is hard. So I've
made you some prompts
in the video planner.
They're just little questions
you can ask yourself
that will jog your
memory. All right. So
now let's look at
the three types of
stories you can tell
to trigger emotion and
connect your point to
something real. So story
one is quite simply
telling a story about
how you solved something.
That should be your
go -to when you've
lived through the problem
you're helping your viewers.
So story two is
going to be a
story that you can
tell to trigger emotion
and connect your point
to something you've solved.
It's simple, it's relatable,
it's real, and it's
going to raise your
credibility to levels others
in your niche can't
compete with. And that's
what makes it so
powerful. Also, because you
openly admit you sucked
at something and had
the viewer's problem, they
actually like you more
than people who pretend
to be perfect. In
fact, I'm at this
weird stage that when
I realize I am
sat on the staircase
of pain, like I
am right now rebuilding
this course, finding everything
very hard. I know
that when I get
out of it, I
am going to have
another epic story to
tell. That's just going
to go my business.
So if I was
going to rank these
for sales power, I'd
give them a two
out of three star,
but why only two
out of three? Well,
because the next type
of story is top
dog for sales and
it gets a three
out of three and
that's story type two.
And this used to
frustrate the heck out
of me because back
when I was doing
all these challenges to
show how you should
actually grow channels, I
was always making videos
about how I was
growing my own channel.
So people used to
comment, oh, of course,
you can do it,
Ed. If you're that
good, do it to
someone else's channel. So
eventually I realized, yeah,
actually they're right. If
I tell stories about
blowing up someone else's
channel, it's even more
proof I'm legit. So
I did. I blew
up a channel, documented
it and insane results,
but I still got
comments going, well, of
course you can blow
up a channel in
that niche. Why not
try it in another
niche instead? Honestly, you
can't win. So this
story is just simply
telling the story of
someone you helped to
get a result. And
I'd use this when
you want to show
viewers that people like
them are already winning
with this information. Bringing
us on to the
next type of story.
This is a great
tool when you don't
have a person example
or a client. This
can work because you
call out your viewers
exact problems in a
relatable way that makes
them feel like you
get them. What you
need to be very
careful is not telling
the same story everyone
else has already told
about Elon Musk. Because
when people hear a
story they already know
the outcome to, there's
no surprise. It's kind
of boring. So how
do you pick which
one to use? Well,
I made a little
decision matrix for you.
So if you want
to show people how
to solve a problem
and you've solved it
for a client and
it's got a strong
transformation, tell that one
first. If you want
to show people how
to solve a problem
you've not solved it
for a client but
you have for yourself,
tell that one. And
if you've got neither,
tell it about anyone
or tell the viewer's
story instead. The viewer's
story is simply putting
them in a situation
like this. So you
sign up for Ed's
program and you're thinking
to yourself, wow, there's
way more to this
than I expected. And
you're starting to feel
a bit overwhelmed. But
you put out your
first demo video, realize
that actually, maybe it's
not as hard as
I thought. And then
you went on to
blow up and become
the world's most famous
person in your niche.
Not as big a
fan of telling the
viewer's story because it's
like a fairy tale
at the end of
the day. But it
still can be effective.
Okay, so now let's
look at the thing
that's going to make
your viewers realize that
the story you told
in the emotion brick
was incredibly smart as
you seamlessly link it
to the actionable steps
that follow in the
logic brick. And to
achieve this, let's bring
back the sexy transition.
All right. So remember,
if you're not a
fan of the logic
brick, you're not going
to be able to
do it. Remember, the
goal of a transition
is to hook forward
to the coming value
and to signal that
the script is moving
on from one section
to another so the
viewers can feel progress.
To do that, once
the story ends, you
use a transition that
might sound like this.
So here's the five
key lessons I learned
from that. Or now
let me show you
how to avoid the
same mistake. Or here's
how you can fix
that yourself. These sort
of transitions signal the
story's over. Now I'm
going to help you.
So when you nail
the transition, the logic
will land 10 times
better because they now
know why they need
to hear and listen
to what follows. And
finally, let's look at
when you should use
story because a lot
of people have heard
me say all of
this wonderful stuff about
it and then try
to shoehorn it into
every video, which can
be like using a
spoon to cut a
steak. So what you
want to do is
follow this decision matrix
if you're unsure if
you even need one
because I'm not telling
you you have to
put them in every
video. I'm telling them
you need to use
them when they are
the best tool for
the job. So the
questions here are, will
this tip feel bland,
overused, or like I've
heard it before? Or
will it be a
little bit more complicated?
And then the next
question is, do I
need the viewer to
feel that's exactly my
struggle? Is the topic
emotionally charged? Am I
asking them to change
a habit or invest
effort or spend money?
If so, use a
story. If not, use
one of the other
visual demos in this
list. Now, if you're
feeling like this is
a lot, that's because
it is. For three
years, I've had a
weekly coaching call with
this guy called John
Boucher. He's a storytelling
coach. I told you
I was really bought
into this. And he
helped me write scripts
for Filmboo, scripts on
my current channel, and
also helped me plan
a ton of the
frameworks in this course.
So I'm going to
give you a little
bit of a look
at that. So I
highly recommend him if
you want to go
next level with your
storytelling. I'll link to
his website below. But
my point is storytelling
isn't something you master
in a day or
even three years. You
have to tell hundreds
of them so that
it starts to feel
natural and they just
come to you quite
easily. And this is
just why so many
people write off as
nonsense because a good
story works, a bad
one doesn't. But if
you want to take
a stranger and turn
them into a fan
or a customer in
under 30 seconds, this
is the way you
do it. Now, when
you start trying this
out, you're going to
naturally get crazy overwhelmed
and question all of
your friends and family.
And you're going to
make crazy decisions because
that's what we do
when we transform into
a Hulk. But don't
worry, just do this.
Fail as fast as
you can, test out
all kinds of stories,
see what resonates, and
you'll know when it's
working because people will
email you or comment
about the exact story
when they do. Everything
else, retention cells, trust
flows from that. Okay,
so when it comes
to planning a story,
there's a little document
here in the video
planning doc with little
prompts and structure. Keep
using the three -step
story planner. Start small
with a little 20
to 30 second stories.
Use the story types
you've learned. Try dropping
them into your next
video if you think
they're needed. And let's
start practicing them and
seeing what happens. And
now we can move
on to the next
video, which is the
third tool we can
use in the emotion
brick.